Dorothy Thompson Collection
Dorothy Thompson Collection
1922-1963
Thompson, Dorothy, 1893-1961.
2 linear ft.
Collection of material relating to the American journalist. Contains articles by and about Thompson, photographs, correspondence, political cartoon, miscellaneous printed and published material.
149448
Biographical History
Dorothy Thompson (1893-1961) was an American broadcast and print journalist, best known for her work as a foreign correspondent and her column "On the Record" that appeared in the New York Herald Tribune from 1936-1941. She graduated from Syracuse University in 1914, where she studied political science and economics, and became one of the few women news commentators on radio during the 1930s. An early and outspoken opponent of Adolf Hitler, she was the first American journalist to be expelled from Nazi Germany in 1934. For a more detailed biography, see the
Dorothy Thompson Papers
at this repository.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Dorothy Thompson Collection consists of awards/citations, correspondence, photographs, printed material, and writings.
Awards and citations recognize Thompson's work for the War Department and with young people.
Correspondence is primarily personal in nature. The bulk is between Thompson and her first husband, Hungarian author Josef Bard. Spanning the end of their marriage (1922-1927), Thompson's romance with and subsequent marriage to Sinclair Lewis, and the rise of Thompson's career, the letters, although of a personal nature, also trace Thompson's journalistic activities through Europe, Russia, and the United States. Other letters include those to artist Eileen Agar (Bard's second wife) and suffragist leader Gertrude Tone, a friend of Thompson's. There is a also a single letter from Sinclair Lewis to Bard and an incoming letter from Ludwig Lewisohn to Bard and Thompson, and some correspondence with Thompson's college friends Ruth Hoople and Winifred ("Win") Hughes. Formats include letters, telegrams, and empty envelopes.
Photographs, most of which were taken during her marriage to Bard, are of Thompson alone or the two of them as a couple.
Printed material consist of books and clippings. The books are primarily history and economics, many of which have annotations, margin notes, etc. in a hand that appears to be Thompson's. Clippings consist of newspaper and magazine articles about Thompson, including obituaries and biographical sketches published on the occasion of her death.
Writings contains columns, articles, and essays by Thompson, some printed and others in manuscript/typescript form. The bulk of this series are typescripts of her "On the Record" colummns, as submitted to Bell Syndicate, and clippings of her articles for Ladies Home Journal. Topics include politics, economics, and current events.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Related Material
See also the
Dorothy Thompson Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Bard, Josef, 1892-; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951.; Thompson, Dorothy, 1893-1961.; Journalists -- Family relationships.; Journalists -- United States.; Women authors, American.; Women journalists -- United States.; Books.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Negatives (photographs); Notebooks.; Photographs.; Authors.; Journalists.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Acquisition Information
Various sources, gift and purchase.
Inventory
- Awards and citations
  - New York University, Class of 1941 award "for distinguished service to the youth of America" (Box 1)
  - War Department citation [missing 5/1/18], 1946 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Lewis, Sinclair, to Josef Bard, 1928 (Box 1)
  - Lewisohn, Lewis, to D. Thompson / J. Bard, 1926 (Box 1)
  - Thompson, Dorothy, to Eileen Agar Bard, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Thompson, Dorothy, to Josef Bard, 1926-1935; 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Thompson, Dorothy, to Josef Bard / Eileen Agar Bard, undated (Box 1)
  - Thompson, Dorothy, to Ruth Hoople, 1913; 1915,; 1922,; 1928,; undated; Thompson's college roommate; includes clipping about Hoople and Thompson, photo of Sinclair Lewis and son Michael, 2 sketches of nude woman (Box 1)
    Gift of Ruth Agnes Hoople, 1968.
  - Thompson, Dorothy, to Ruth Hoople, undated; includes typescript, "Dorothy Thompson as told by her roommate, Ruth Hoople" (Box 1)
    Transfer from University Archives, 1969.
  - Thompson, Dorothy, to Winifred Hughes, 1914; 1937-1940; all but one letter are photocopies; includes original photograph of 1914 SU women's basketball team (with names), including Thompson and Hughes (Box 1)
    Gift of Winifred Hughes, 1979.
  - Thompson, Dorothy, to Dr. Bernard Pacella, 1960; lengthy letter detailing Thompson's concerns about her son Michael Lewis; includes clipping about incident involving a cutlass (Box 1)
    Transfer from Mari Sandoz High Plains Heritage Center, 2017.
  - Thompson, Dorothy, to Gertrude Tone, undated (Box 1)
  - Thompson, Dorothy, to multiple recipients, 1956; 1958; to Agatha, Hilda, Alex, Charlotte, Mike and Benny, Peg and Howard (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Dorothy Thompson, 1922; 1927,; undated (Box 1)
    "Dorothy Thompson Budapest 1922"; "Frau Dr. Bard"; Dorothy Thompson (with envelope dated 30 Mar 1927); Dorothy Thompson, signed and inscribed from Thompson to Bard, Jul 1927; Dorothy Thompson in canoe
  - Dorothy Thompson and Josef Bard, undated; print, copy negative (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Clippings
    - Clippings about Thompson, 1931; 1937-1938,; 1940,; 1957,; 1961,; 1963,; undated (Box 2)
    - Clippings on Thompson's death, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Clippings about Michael Lewis (son of Thompson and Sinclair Lewis), 1966 (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Articles, Ladies Home Journal, 1938-1942; 1960-1961; clippings; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Column, "On the Record," Bell Features Syndicate, 1938-1939; undated; clippings (Box 2)
  - Column, "On the Record," Bell Features Syndicate, 1956 Apr-Dec; typescript, as submitted (Box 2)
  - Column, "On the Record," Bell Features Syndicate, 1957 Jan, Mar-Dec; typescript, as submitted; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Column, "On the Record," Bell Features Syndicate, 1958 Jan-Aug; typescript, as submitted; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Essay [?], The only kind of peace, undated; typescript carbon (Box 2)
  - Notebook, undated; small spiral-bound with handwritten list of articles (Box 2)
  - Pamphlet, "The Lincoln Papers", undated; limited edition letterpress reprint of one of Thompson's columns; printed by The Pony Barn Press in Warrenville, Illinois (Box 2)